Today we're looking at our new widget plant
being built at Southside. I've asked Barbara
to report on progress and bring us up to date
and up to speed. Barbara?
Thanks Denise. I'll just outline the process
we've been through, identify some problems,
and give you an estimate on completion time
and the outcome financially.
Is it good news or bad news?
Bear with me. Now, if you recall, after a
feasibility study, we put the project out
to tender eighteen months ago, and selected
Ezybuild as our project manager.
Work commenced about fifteen months ago, and
it's been progressing to schedule until recently.
What's the problem?
Unfortunately there are three: Firstly, there's
been a delay in materials - specifically steel
because of industrial issues at the suppliers.
Secondly, we've lost days due to the weather.
And finally, there's been a resulting cost
blowout.
So what are we going to do?
Well, they've managed to get another supplier
now. I suggested moving the completion date
back. That way, there's no penalty, and they
agreed to re-deploy their workers until building
can start again.
Smart thinking.
We've been waiting for the rain to stop - but
we can't control the weather!
And the cost?
At this stage, just a small overage. But I'll
be watching it very closely over the next
few months. With no more delays, we're expecting
to complete the project just one month behind
schedule.
Good work Barbara.
Humph
Today's episode is a focussed meeting with
a specific purpose. Barbara has been asked
to report on the progress of a project. Our
focus today is on the verb tenses she uses
to report. Firstly, let's look at how Denise
asks for Barbara's report.
Today we're looking today at our new widget
plant being built at Southside. I've asked
Barbara to report on progress and bring us
all up to date and up to speed.
Denise says, "Today we're looking at our new
widget plant."
She uses the present continuous tense, 'we're
looking' or 'we are looking' because she's
telling them what they are doing, and what
they are going to do at the meeting now.
She doesn't use the simple present 'we look',
because that is used for regular actions.
Then she says, "I've asked Barbara to report."
She uses the present perfect tense, 'I have
asked' because she asked Barbara to report
before the meeting, and Barbara is about to
give her report.
We'll look more at present perfect later.
And she wants Barbara to bring them 'up to
date' and 'up to speed'.
These are common expressions. To bring someone
'up to date' is to tell them what has happened
up to the present. And to bring someone 'up
to speed' is to make sure they know all the
relevant facts.
How does Barbara respond?
Thanks Denise. I'll just outline the process
we've been through, identify some problems,
and give you an estimate on completion time
and the outcome financially.
She says, "I'll just outline the process."
She uses the future tense, I will, because
she's talking about something she's going
to do in the next few minutes. Notice that
the 'will' is not repeated, but it applies
to all three of the things she says she is
going to do.
Let's see how Barbara reports on progress.
Now, if you recall, after a feasibility study,
we put the project out to tender eighteen
months ago, and selected Ezybuild as our project
manager.
Because Barbara is describing events in the
past, she uses the simple past tense.
We put the project out to tender.
We selected Ezybuild as the project manager.
These events happened in the past, and they
are finished.
Work commenced about fifteen months ago, and
it's been progressing to schedule until recently.
Again we see the simple past in the phrase:
Work commenced about fifteen months ago. The
work started at a particular time in the past.
But look at the next phrase: "It's been progressing
to schedule."
When we look at continuous events - things
that happen over a period of time, we use
a continuous tense. The work started in the
past, and it has continued until the present.
This is called the present perfect continuous
tense. It's here is short for, it has. Try
some other examples with Barbara.
Work's been going on since last year.
We've been monitoring progress continuously.
I've been checking the work regularly.
Now let's look at how Barbara describes the
three problems.
Firstly, there's been a delay in materials
- specifically steel because of industrial
issues at the suppliers. Secondly, we've lost
days due to the weather. And finally, there's
been a cost blowout.
Notice the verb tense Barbara uses.
there's been a delay
we've lost days
there's been a cost blowout
These are all present perfect verbs, using
'has' or 'have'.
there has been
we have lost
Present perfect tense is used to describe
events which began in the past and are still
true now.
In business it can be important to use the
correct verb tense. Using the wrong one can
change the meaning. For example, if Barbara
said, "There was a delay", it means this delay
happened in the past, and there is no delay
now.
If she says, "there is a delay", she means
that delay is still happening - they are still
losing time.
But if she says "there has been a delay",
she means the delay started in the past and
has continued up until the present. But as
we'll see, she is now fixing the problem.
Well, they've managed to get another supplier
now. I suggested moving the completion date
back. That way, there's no penalty, and they
agreed to re-deploy their workers until building
can start again.
Let's look at the verb tenses here:
"They've managed to get another supplier."
They managed to get another supplier in the
past, and that supplier is still now supplying
the materials.
I suggested moving the completion date back.
She suggested it at a particular time in the
past.
There's no penalty. There is no penalty now.
They agreed to redeploy their workers. They
agreed at a particular time in the past. Redeployed
means they were sent to work somewhere else.
Look now at the last part of the scene.
We've been waiting for the rain to stop, but
we can't control the weather!
And the cost?
At this stage, just a small overage. But I'll
be watching it very closely over the next
few months. With no more delays, we're expecting
to complete the project just one month behind
schedule.
Here we see some examples of continuous tenses
to help meaning.
We've been waiting - We have been waiting
for the rain to stop, and we are still waiting.
I'll be watching - I will be watching in the
future over a long time.
We're expecting - we are expecting at the
moment, and we will continue to expect in
the future.
Notice also how Denise asks a question.
But we can't control the weather! And the
cost?
She says, "and the cost?" The upward inflection
in her voice, "and the cost?" tells us this
is a question, although it's not a complete
sentence. The complete sentence would be,
"What will it cost?" In spoken English, this
is very common.
Practise some examples with Denise.
And the cost?
And the result?
And the reason?
Today we looked at reporting back. Remember,
first summarise what you are going to report
on. We also focussed on the different verb
tenses, which help exact meaning.
That's all we have time for today, so I hope
we'll be seeing you next time for The Business
of English.